Maria Fernanda Ibarra Gutiérrez



CURP: IAGF890825MDFBTR07 Nationality: Mexican Birth Date: 25 August 1989

Sex: Female E-mail:

mariafernanda.ibarragutierrez@postgrad.manchester.ac.uk

Statistical analysis of data has interested me for the whole of my career. Moreover, I have experience with collected and systematized information through tools programming. I have a specific interest in the analysis of information and implementation of mathematical models to explain social, demographic and risk phenomena.

Values Honesty Responsibility Leadership Other interest Reading Traveling

Education and qualifications

University of Manchester 2019-2023

School of Social Science.

PhD student of Data Analytics and Society.

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) 2009-2013

Science Faculty.

Bachelor's degree in Actuarial Science.

Modules included a deep background of mathematical and statistical modelling.

Courses.

2019 – Summer School on Multidimensional Poverty Analysis by Oxford Poverty and Human Development Initiative (OPHI) University of Oxford.

2018 - Multivariate Methods by the Mathematics Research Centre, S.C.

2018 - Crime Victimization Surveys by UNODC.

2018 - How to read and process gender data using R? By Civic Data.

2018 - Record Linkage Workshop by the Mathematics Research Centre, S.C.

2017 - Online Certified Introduction to Feminist Theory and Research by the National Autonomous University of Mexico.

2016 - Colloquium on Feminist and Gender Studies (Women and Violence: Intersectionality) by the University of Brasilia.

2016 - Certified in Probability and Statistics from the National Autonomous University of Mexico.

2015 - Certified in Statistics by Actuary Hunter.

2015 - Certified in Applications of Data Mining by the Technological Institute and Higher Education of Monterrey.

2014 - Course on Statistics in R by Applied Mathematics and Actuary Training.

2014 - Seminar on Classical Foundations of Feminist Thought 1 by Construction and Gender Analysis Research and Teaching Centre S.C.

2013 - Certified in Human Rights by the Human Rights Centre "Fray Francisco de Vittoria".

2013 - Intensive Workshop in Mathematical Models Applied to Research in Social Sciences with Special Orientation to Political Science by the National Autonomous University of Mexico.

2013 - Course of Operational Risk Management 2 by NUMERAVI Risk valuation and analysis S.C.

2012 - Course of Operational Risk Management 1 by NUMERAVI Risk valuation and analysis S.C.

Computational qualifications.

R: advanced level. STATA: basic level SPSS: medium level.

Tableau: Visualizations, basic level.

SAS: basic level. MySQL: medium level.

Visual Fox Pro: medium level, knowledge of programming language in Fox Pro 9.0.

Languages.

International English Language Testing System (IELTS) 6.5

Certification of English Language for Foreigners TOEFL (paper based) 563.

 $\label{lem:certification} \textbf{Certification of Portuguese Language for Foreigners CELPE}.$

Employment experience

INSTITUTE OF RESEARCH ON SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT AND SOCIAL EQUITY OF THE IBEROAMERICAN UNIVERSITY (EQUIDE) Present

NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF STATISTIC AND GEOGRAPHY (INEGI) 05/01/2017 to 05/31/2018 General Directorate of Government, Public Safety and Justice Statistics

BANK OF MEXICO 07/09/2013 to 06/30/2016 General Directorate of Emission

BANK OF MEXICO 10/30/2012 to 4/30/2013 General Directorate of Emission

Quantitative Research Assistant

- Support the theoretical and methodological construction of the multidimensional measurement of urban poverty.
- Cleaning and processing databases.
- Statistical analysis.

Link of Methodological Support.

- Generation of databases based on INEGI censuses and surveys.
- Generation and validation of indicators related to public safety, gender, violence, poverty, corruption, among others.
- Generation of visualizations based on the indicators.
- Methodological support for documents and presentations.
- Calculation of SDG-ONU indicators.

Risk and Control Analyst.

- Data analysis for operational risk assessment.
- Implementation of statistical models for the measurement of operational risk.
- Tools programming to gather information.
- Systematization of information.
- Generation of Indicators.

Fellow in the Risk and Control Division.

- Homogenization of the operational risk incident matrix.
- Cost-benefit analysis of values transfer insurance.